Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society records, 1786-1954.
Congregational Library & Archives
Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society records, 1786-1954.
RG0120
Congregational Library & Archives
.97 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
This collection contains various records from The Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society which formed on March 24, 1786, when their Act of Incorporation was passed and signed. The Society served and continues to serve as financial support for widows and children of deceased Congregational ministers, and this is reflected in the collection in the form of grant applications, correspondence with beneficiaries, and financial statements.
Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society
Maine Congregational Charitable Society
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Historical Note
Beginning as a fund within the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers, The Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society formed on March 24, 1786, when their Act of Incorporation was passed and signed. After incorporation, the Society maintained a close relationship to the Convention who continued to contribute funds to the Society. The aim of the Society was to provide annual financial relief for widows and children of deceased Congregational ministers.
In the early 19th century, Congregationalism in New England split into two distinct wings. The Charitable Society continued to serve both without interruption, and still currently serve both the families of Unitarian Universalist and United Church of Christ ministers. Shortly after 1820 when Maine achieved statehood, a separate Maine Congregational Charitable Society was incorporated, although today the funds from the Massachusetts Society support families in both states.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various records created by the Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society from its inception in 1786. It is comprised of financial and administrative records.
Arrangement
The Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society records have been arranged into the two series listed below. Within each series materials have been primarily arranged in chronological order by start date. When appropriate, similar and continuous materials have been grouped together.
Series 1: Finances, 1787-1917
Series 2: Administration, 1786-1954
Related Materials
Additional records related to the Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society can be found at the Harvard Divinity School Library, bMS 00504 and the Massachusetts Historical Society, Ms. N-511.
Bibliography
"An historical sketch of the Convention of the Congregational Ministers in Massachusetts: with an account of its funds, its connexion with the Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society, and its rules and regulations, MDCCCXXI. (1821), 9.3 2047. The Congregational Library & Archives, Boston, MA."
Charity; Church societies.; Clergy; Congregationalism--New England; Corporate minutes.; Correspondence.; Financial Statements; Widows--United States--Economic conditions; Massachusetts Congregational Charitable Society; Maine Congregational Charitable Society
- Finances, 1787 1917; 1787-1917; 14 Items
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains financial records in the form of both paper reports and 2 volumes. This includes Treasurer's Reports, donation information, and beneficiary information.
  - Bequest Information, 1787 1857; 1787-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 1810 1821; 1810-1821 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 1822 1839; 1822-1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial Statements, 1841 1860; 1841-1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1861 1875; 1861-1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial Statements, 1877 1896; 1877-1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1896 1917; 1896-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1817 1856; 1817-1856 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1858 1873; 1858-1873 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1867 1871; 1867-1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1880 1885; 1880-1885 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1886 1899; 1886-1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1886 1903; 1886-1903 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Beneficiary Information, 1901 1917; 1901-1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Administration, 1786 1954; 1786-1954; 17 Folders
  This series contains internal administrative records such as committee reports, acts of incorporation, by-laws, and meeting minutes. It also contains all correspondence with beneficiaries and members, including grant applications sent by families of deceased ministers.
  - Internal Policies & Membership, 1786 1889; 1786-1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1807 1813; 1807, 1813 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Assorted Meeting Minutes, 1820 1829; 1820, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Maine Congregational Charitable Society, 1821 1839; 1821-1839 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee Reports, 1851 1862; 1851-1852, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Internal Administration, 1860 1903; 1860-1903 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Correspondence, 1867 1903; 1867-1903 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers, 1868 1893; 1868-1893 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Applications, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Applications, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Applications, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Applications, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Applications, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Applications, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Applications, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Death Notices, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)